Guide to the Jack Gelber Papers 1938-2002 (Bulk 1957-1999) MSS.146
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series II: Production Files
  - Subseries P: Plays Directed
    - "Night Music" by Clifford Odets, Script (Annotated Photocopy), and Production Materials, Undated (Box 38, Folder 1086)
      The script is a photocopy from Night Music: A Comedy in Twelve Scenes, by Clifford Odets, New York: Random House, c1940; For Oversize Material See: Series IIP Oversize, Box 50, Folder 1219
    - "Carl and the Professor" (by Wendy Hammond), New York University Tisch School of the Arts Program, 1984-1985 (Box 38, Folder 1087)
    - "The Old Flag: A Play in Two Acts" by Vincent Canby (Typescript), 1985 (Box 38, Folder 1088)
    - "Dream of a Blacklisted Actor" by Conrad Bromberg (Bound Annotated Typescript) and Production Materials, 1986, Undated (Box 38, Folder 1089)
    - "Mink on a Gold Hook," (by James Ryan) Sample Tape Track List (Annotated) and Clipping, 1986 (Box 38, Folder 1090)
    - "The Stalwarts" (by OyamO), Ensemble Studio Theatre Program and Flyer, 1990 (Box 38, Folder 1091)
    - "Chinese Coffee" (by Ira Lewis), Ensemble Studio Theatre Flyer and Program, 1990 (Box 38, Folder 1092)
    - "George Washington Dances" (by David Margulies) Ensemble Studio Theatre, Review, 1992 (Box 38, Folder 1093)
    - "If Only I Could Remember My Name" (by Robert Siegel) Ensemble Studio Theatre, Flyer, 1992 (Box 38, Folder 1094)
    - "Born Guilty" (by Ari Roth) Review and Program, 1993 (Box 38, Folder 1095)
    - "I'm With Ya, Duke" (by Herb Gardner), Ensemble Studio Theatre, Reviews, 1994 (Box 38, Folder 1096)
  - Subseries Q: Film Scripts
    - "The Great Escape," First Typed Version (Annotated Typescript), 1964 (Box 38, Folder 1097)
      The document is marked "For Booker and Foster"
    - "Original 'Dill Pickle'" (Annotated Typescript) and Notes, [1969?] (Box 39, Folder 1098)
    - "Dill Pickle" (Annotated Typescript), 1969? (Box 39, Folder 1099)
    - "Dill Pickle," Notes and Recipient List, Undated (Box 39, Folder 1100)
    - "On the Take: A Screenplay" (Bound Typescript), Undated (Box 39, Folder 1101)
      The script is marked "Sagonopack Films"
    - "On the Take" (Bound Typescript), 1969 (Box 39, Folder 1102)
    - "On the Take" (Bound Annotated Typescript), 1969 (Box 39, Folder 1103)
    - "Charlie Siringo, Shooting Draft" (Annotated Typescript), [1976] (Box 39, Folder 1104)
    - "Charlie Siringo" (Typescript), with Revised Pages, 1976 (Box 39, Folder 1105)
    - "Charlie Siringo," Journal Entry for January 9, 1977 (Box 40, Folder 1106)
    - "I'll Take Manhattan, or Two Bridges" (Annotated Typescript), 1981 (Box 40, Folder 1107)
    - "Take Manhattan: Manhattan Take" (Typescript), 1984 (Box 40, Folder 1108)
    - "Take Manhattan: Manhattan Take" (Bound Typescript), 1984 (Box 40, Folder 1109)
    - "Take Manhattan: Manhattan Take" (Bound Typescript) and Notes, 1984, Undated (Box 40, Folder 1110)
    - "Take Manhattan: Manhattan Take" (Bound Annotated Typescript), 1984 (Box 40, Folder 1111)
    - "Double Trouble" Precis (Typescript), 1984 (Box 40, Folder 1112)
    - "Out for the Count" (Annotated Typescripts), Notes, and a Clipping, 1984-1985, Undated (Box 40, Folder 1113)
      Some of the notes in this folder were written on the reverse of a letter signed Cesar Chavez
    - "Mother of the Bride, Working Copy" (Annotated Typescript), Notes, and a Flyer, 1989, Undated (Box 41, Folder 1114)
      Many of the notes held in this folder were written on the reverse of copies of two letters from Jack and Carol Gelber, one addressed to Jeremy Zimmer and the other to Jane Sindell
    - "Russian Hill" (Annotated Typescript) and Notes, 1990-1993, Undated (Box 41, Folder 1115)
    - "Coming Attractions" (Typescripts) and Notes, Undated (Box 41, Folder 1116)
      Most of the screenplays included in this folder are annotated
    - "Hope, Rising Expectations, and the Obsessive Image", Undated (Box 41, Folder 1117)
    - "'Jelly Roll' Notes", 1938-1966, Undated (Box 41, Folder 1118)
    - "Jelly Roll" (Bound Typescript), Undated (Box 41, Folder 1119)
      This version consists of 116 pages
    - "Jelly Roll" (Bound Typescript), Undated (Box 41, Folder 1120)
      This version consists of 130 pages
    - "Midnight Cowboy, Second Gelber Draft" (Bound Annotated Typescript), Undated (Box 41, Folder 1121)
    - "Midnight Cowboy, First Version" (Bound Annotated Typescript), Undated (Box 42, Folder 1122)
    - "Rio Hacha" Precis (Two Typescripts), Undated (Box 42, Folder 1123)
      The second item is annotated
    - "Two Birds With One Stone" Precis (Typescript), Undated (Box 42, Folder 1124)
    - Untitled Screenplay (Typescript), Undated (Box 42, Folder 1125)
  - Subseries R: Other Manuscripts
    - "Beginner's Luck" (Typescript), Undated (Box 42, Folder 1126)
    - "The Birthday Party" (Typescript), Undated (Box 42, Folder 1127)
      See Also: "Early College Stuff" (Series IIR, Box 42, Folder 1133)
    - "Button, Button" (Two Typescripts), Undated (Box 42, Folder 1128)
    - "By the Way, My Name is Roger Soames" (Typescript and Two Pages from a Handwritten Version), Undated (Box 42, Folder 1129)
      The handwritten pages were written on the reverse of a letter from Gelber to Show Magazine
    - "Diary of a Scoundrel, Original" Pages 1-114 (Annotated Typescript) and Notes, 1977 (Box 42, Folder 1130)
    - "Diary of a Scoundrel, Original" Pages 115-208 (Annotated Typescript), 1977 (Box 42, Folder 1131)
    - "Diary of a Scoundrel" Notes and Pages 1-45 (Annotated Typescript), 1979, Undated (Box 42, Folder 1132)
    - "Early College Stuff:" Poems, Short Stories, and Notes (Typescripts, Annotated Typescripts, and Manuscripts), Undated (Box 42, Folder 1133)
    - "Edinburgh" (Two Annotated Typescripts) and Notes, Undated (Box 43, Folder 1134)
    - "Foolish Wives," (Three Typescripts and One Manuscript Version), Undated (Box 43, Folder 1135)
    - "Getting It, or On the Make in Sunny Spain" (Two Typescripts), Undated (Box 43, Folder 1136)
    - "Hanging On" (Two Typescripts), Undated (Box 43, Folder 1137)
    - "The King of Shades, Corrected Copy" (Typescript), Undated (Box 43, Folder 1138)
    - "Leslie in New York, or an Essay on Scuffling" (Typescript), Undated (Box 43, Folder 1139)
    - "Maison Blanc, or The Big Whitey" (Annotated Typescript), Undated (Box 43, Folder 1140)
    - "The Marilyn Project" (Annotated Typescripts) and Notes, 1973-1974, Undated (Box 43, Folder 1141)
    - "Mystery" (Two Annotated Typescripts), Undated (Box 43, Folder 1142)
    - "Neal vs. Jimmy the Fag" (Two Typescripts) and a Copy of the Evergreen Review (December 1964), 1964, Undated (Box 43, Folder 1143)
    - "Nile's Gig" (Typescript), Undated (Box 43, Folder 1144)
    - "The Notebooks of Jimmy Singer" Pages 1-133 (Annotated Typescript) and Notes, Undated (Box 43, Folder 1145)
    - "The Notebooks of Jimmy Singer" Pages 134-254 (Annotated Typescript), Undated (Box 43, Folder 1146)
    - "The Notebooks of Jimmy Singer" Pages 255-405 (Annotated Typescript), Undated (Box 43, Folder 1147)
    - "The Obsessive Image" (Typescript), Undated (Box 43, Folder 1148)
    - "On the Home Front" (Three Typescripts), Undated (Box 43, Folder 1149)
      The first item is annotated
    - "Orange Peels" (Annotated Typescript), Undated (Box 44, Folder 1150)
    - "Order of Priority" (Two Typescripts), Undated (Box 44, Folder 1151)
    - "Part I" (Two Typescripts), Undated (Box 44, Folder 1152)
    - "Picking the Chicken" (Clipping), 1963 (Box 44, Folder 1153)
      Clipped from Nugget Volume 8, Number 5 (November 1963), New York: Fly Eagle Publications, Inc, 1963
    - "Playwright as Shaman: Sam Shepard" (Annotated Typescript), Undated (Box 44, Folder 1154)
    - "Playwright's Dilemma" (Typescript), 1979 (Box 44, Folder 1155)
      This folder also includes a "Participants" list for The East-West Center's "Global Situation: The Writer in the Twentieth Century, December 10-20, 1979"
    - "The Purple Rider" (Annotated Typescript), Undated (Box 44, Folder 1156)
    - "Satisfaction" (Two Typescripts), Undated (Box 44, Folder 1157)
    - "A Shot At Immortality" (Typescript), Undated (Box 44, Folder 1158)
    - "A Shot At Immortality" (Typescript) and a Sketch, Undated (Box 44, Folder 1159)
    - "The Sunflower" (Two Typescripts), Undated (Box 44, Folder 1160)
    - "Le Surnaturel Social" (Two Photocopies), 1967 (Box 44, Folder 1161)
      The document is a photocopy of a section from Les USA A La Recherche de Leur Identite, Pierre Dommergues, ed., [Paris:] Grasset, 1967
    - "The Ultimate Paranoia" (Typescript), Undated (Box 44, Folder 1162)
    - "Untitled First Drafts" (Typescripts), Undated (Box 44, Folder 1163)
    - Untitled and Fragments, Undated (Box 44, Folder 1164)
      This folder holds handwritten and typescript short stories, poems, and a play
  - Subseries S: Biographical Material
    - "Ideas", 1980-1985, Undated (Box 44, Folder 1165)
      The items in this folder appear to describe a number of Jack Gelber's writings, including "Chambers," "Rio Preserved," "Magic Valley," and "Diary of A Scoundrel." The materials consist of news clippings, annotated typescripts, notes, short stories, and a precis entitled "Hot Potato."
    - Biographical Clippings, 1959 (Box 44, Folder 1166)
      For Oversize Materials See: Series IIS Oversize, Box 50, Folder 1220
    - Biographical and News Clippings, 1960 (Box 44, Folder 1167)
    - Biographical and News Clippings, 1961-1971 (Box 44, Folder 1168)
      For Oversize Material See: Series IIS Oversize, Box 50, Folder 1221
    - Biographical and News Clippings, Programs, and a Map of New York City, 1972-1978 (Box 44, Folder 1169)
      For Oversize Material See: Series IIS Oversize, Box 50, Folder 1222
    - News Clippings, 1979-1982 (Box 44, Folder 1170)
      For Oversize Material See: Series IIS, Box 50, Folder 1223
    - Biographical and News Clippings, a Photograph, and Notes, Undated (Box 44, Folder 1171)
      This folder includes an untitled photograph of Gelber posing with six unidentified men, and a page of notes that may pertain to "The Connection;" For Oversize Material See: Series IIS, Box 50, Folder 1224
    - Small Notebook, 1978, Undated (Box 44, Folder 1172)
      This item contains original sketches, notes (possibly regarding "The Cuban Thing"), and a handwritten draft of a letter of recommendation for "[Cronshi B.]."
    - Journal Entries, 1961, 1987, Undated (Box 45, Folder 1173)
    - "Biography of Jack Gelber" by Unknown Author (Annotated Typescript), Undated (Box 45, Folder 1174)
      The document is annotated with the following information: "Pls. return: Walter Alford, John Springer Assoc."
    - Experimental Theatre: Notes and a Drawing, Undated (Box 45, Folder 1175)
    - "Introduction" by Richard Gilman (Photocopy), Undated (Box 45, Folder 1176)
      The document is marked "In Press Richard Seaver Books, Viking Press as Introduction to The Apple and Square in the Eye"
- Series III: Calendars and Datebooks
  - unspecified
    - Datebook, 1965 (Box 45, Folder 1177)
    - Datebook, 1969 (Box 45, Folder 1178)
      For Calendars from the year 1971 see Series III Oversize, Box 50, Folder 1225
    - Datebooks and Calendars, 1975-1979 (Box 45, Folder 1179)
    - Datebooks, 1980-1982 (Box 45, Folder 1180)
    - Datebook, 1983 (Box 45, Folder 1181)
    - Datebooks, 1984 (Box 45, Folder 1182)
    - Datebook, 1985 (Box 45, Folder 1183)
    - Datebook, 1986 (Box 46, Folder 1184)
    - Datebooks, 1987-1990 (Box 46, Folder 1185)
    - Datebooks, 1990-1992 (Box 46, Folder 1186)
    - Datebooks, 1992-1996 (Box 46, Folder 1187)
    - Datebooks, 1996-1997 (Box 46, Folder 1188)
    - Calendar, 1998 (Box 46, Folder 1189)
- Series IV: Video
  - Subseries A: Access Copies
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
    - "Siringo Tapes" (Annotated Folder), Undated (Box 46, Folder 1190)
  - Subseries B: Original Cassettes
    - "'Siringo' (Copy) Pt. 1;" 00:30:00; 3/4" Umatic Videocassette, Undated (Box 47, Folder 146.0001)
    - "'Siringo' (Copy) Pt. 2:" 00:60:00; 3/4" Umatic Videocassette, Undated (Box 47, Folder 146.0002)
- Series V: Audio
  - Subseries A: Access Copies
    Audio materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
  - Subseries B: Original Reels
    - [1] "Side 2-985-: First Session About 241?, Vilt Monologues" [2] "Side 2-985-: Second Session 241-650, King Pieces" [3] "Side 2-985-: Third Session 650-932, Jokes-[Standing] Comedy" [4] "Side 1: Fourth Session 0-264, Improvisations" [5] "Side 1: Sixth Session 264-727, Comic Books-Steve [Tesch]" [6] "Seventh Session 720-1000, BJ's Scenes Read;" 1/4" audio reel and Notes, Undated (Box 47, Folder 146.0003)
    - Untitled; 1/4" audio reel, Undated (Box 47, Folder 146.0004)
- Oversize
  Scope and Contents note
  Oversize materials from all preceding series are listed here.
  - Oversize Series I, Subseries A
    - "Conferenza Internazionale Droga e Produzione Artistica" Poster and "Bologna: 3 Days" Brochure, 1983, Undated (Folder 2)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IA, Box 3, Folder 149
    - East Coast Arts at Wildcliff, Direct Mail, 1987-1988 (Box 48, Folder 1192)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IA, Box 3, Folder 192
    - Maps of Valdez, Alaska, 1998 (Box 48, Folder 1193)
      The third item in this folder is annotated; The contents of this folder were removed from Series IA, Box 9, Folder 522
    - "Writing Workshops Summer 1977, Sun Valley Center for the Arts and Humanities" Advertisement (Box 48, Folder 1194)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IA, Box 11, Folder 648
  - Oversize Series I, Subseries C
    - Biographical Clippings and "Maps: Aspen and Snowmass (Colorado)", 1982-1999 (Box 48, Folder 1195)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IC, Box 14, Folder 866
  - Oversize Series II, Subseries A
    - "Camden Jazz Festival, Hampstead Theatre Club" Poster, 1974 (Box 48, Folder 1196)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIA, Box 15, Folder 877
    - Two British Newspapers, 1974 (Box 48, Folder 1197)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIA, 15, 880
    - "The Cultural Innovators" by Spencer Klaw, 1960 (Box 48, Folder 1198)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIA, 16, 894
    - Clippings, 1960 (Box 48, Folder 1199)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIA, Box 16, Folder 895
    - Clipping, 1961 (Box 48, Folder 1200)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIA, Box 17, Folder 896
    - Photocopies of Reviews and Publicity, 1961 (Box 48, Folder 1201)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIA, Box 17, Folder 897
    - Photocopies of Reviews and Publicity, 1962 (Box 48, Folder 1202)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIA, Box 17, Folder 898
    - Club La Martinique Poster and "Conferenza Internazionale Droga e Produzione Artistica" Poster, 1973-1983 (Folder 3)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIA, Box 17, Folder 899
    - Clippings and Advertisements, Undated (Box 48, Folder 1204)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIA, Box 17, Folder 900
    - Scrapbook, 1959-1999, Undated (Box 49)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIA, Box 17, Folder 903
  - Oversize Series II, Subseries B
    - Review, 1962 (Box 50, Folder 1205)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIB, Box 18, Folder 910
    - Clipping, 1961 (Box 50, Folder 1206)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIB, Box 18, Folder 912
    - Living Theatre Poster, Undated (Box 50, Folder 1207)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIB, Box 18, Folder 914
  - Oversize Series II, Subseries C
    - Cover Art Proof, Undated (Box 50, Folder 1208)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIC, Box 19, Folder 921
  - Oversize Series II, Subseries E
    - "The Cuban Thing" (Empty Binder), 1968 (Box 50, Folder 1209)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIE, Box 21, Folder 939
  - Oversize Series II, Subseries F
    - Clipping and "1972 Traverse Festival Late Shows" Annotated Poster (Box 50, Folder 1210)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIF, Box 23, Folder 954
  - Oversize Series II, Subseries J
    - Set Design Sketches (Photocopies), Undated (Box 50, Folder 1211)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIJ, Box 30, Folder 1008
  - Oversize Series II, Subseries K
    - Clippings, 1989 (Box 50, Folder 1212)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIK, Box 32, Folder 1024
  - Oversize Series II, Subseries L
    - Clippings, 1993-1994, Undated (Box 50, Folder 1213)
      The first item is annotated; The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIL, Box 32, Folder 1027
  - Oversize Series II, Subseries P
    - "Indians," Production Materials, Undated (Folder 4)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIP, Box 36, Folder 1060
    - "The Kid," Clipping, 1973 (Box 50, Folder 1215)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIP, Box 37, Folder 1067
    - "Seduced," Annotated Envelope, 1978 (Box 50, Folder 1216)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIP, Box 37, Folder 1075
    - "Seduced," Reviews, 1979 (Box 50, Folder 1217)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIP, Box 37, Folder 1077
    - "The Man and the Fly," Clipping (Spanish language), 1982 (Box 50, Folder 1218)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIP, Box 38, Folder 1082
    - "NYU Salutes Group Theatre 1931-1940: Night Music," Poster, Undated (Box 50, Folder 1219)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIP, Box 38, Folder 1086
  - Oversize Series II, Subseries S
    - Biographical Clipping, 1959 (Box 50, Folder 1220)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIS, Box 44, Folder 1166
    - Biographical Clippings, 1961-1964 (Box 50, Folder 1221)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIS, Box 44, Folder 1168
    - "New York and Vicinity" Map, 1974 (Box 50, Folder 1222)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIS, Box 44, Folder 1169
    - News Clippings, 1979-1980 (Box 50, Folder 1223)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIS, Box 44, Folder 1171
    - News Clippings, Undated (Box 50, Folder 1224)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series IIS, Box 44, Folder 1173
  - Oversize Series III
    - Calendars, 1971 (Box 50, Folder 1225)
      The contents of this folder were removed from Series III, Box 45, Folder 1178